## Jorge Orpinel Perez

Independent Software Engineering Contractor / Consultant / Digital Nomad

Website: http://jorge.orpinel.com
Email: jorge@orpinel.com

I help my clients bring their projects to fruition from inception to launch. I'm an experienced tech lead who can manage the full SDLC of a project. My career is focused on web technologies (full-stack) with a scalability-focus.

I can help produce requirements, technical documentation, plan the project, find the right team and tools for the job, and of course implement it all. REST APIs, SDKs, test-driven development, release management, project/product management, system architecture; programming efficient, scalable, clean code; and continuous integration, APM and DevOps are some of my specialties.

**EXPERIENCE** 

Dev Spotlight Mar 2018 to Present

**Freelance Technical Writer** 

At devspotlight.com we create marketing content for a variety of well-known brands in the technology field. My work focuses on Web Development, DevOps and Application Performance Monitoring and has been featured in publications such as Monitoring Weekly.

APM, Logging, Syslog, Solarwinds AppOptics, Papertrail, Loggly, Pingdom, Selenium, Headless Chrome

Hammock Feb 2017 to Present

**Software Engineering Consultant** 

We're developing the Hammock system to revolutionize small business bookkeeping. Amazon Lambda, Python, Django, AWS, OAuth, REST API (QuickBooks Online), Webhooks

### **Alternative Data Group**

Apr 2018 to Nov 2018

**Lead Software Engineer** 

ADG develops alternative data services for financial institutions. I managed a distributed team of developers, hands-on the code. My job was to keep the team efficient and effective, while architecting and documenting our systems continuously. I also wrote client-facing documentation for the product.

Python, REST API, CI/CD, SQL, Data Analysis, GitLab, AWS, Swawgger (OpenAPI Specification), Asana, Agile, FinTech

## PeopleMovers.com

Oct 2016 to Sep 2017

Lead Developer

\* Project Management and Recruiter (fluctuating team of 2-6)

GitHub Issue Tracking and Projects (Kanban Flow) \* Full Stack Development of the peoplemovers.com web application and API.

PHP, Codelgniter, HTML/CSS/Javascript, AngularJS, Less, MySQL, CloudFlare CDN, AWS Elastic Beanstack, Amazon Cloud Search, i18n \* Business Analysis and Technical Documentation System Requirements, Story Lines, Uses Cases,

Gonebusy

Jan 2017 to Apr 2017

**Contract Software Engineer** 

I built a PHP SDK test suite (https://github.com/gonebusy/gonebusy-php-client/tree/master/test) with PHPUnit and PHP CodeSniffer for basic linting. I continue to consult with the company for other PHP-related tasks as they grow into a successful web booking service provider.

#### FleishmanHillard

Mar 2016 to Jun 2016

**Independent Software Developer** 

\* Expert intervention on translation (i18n) of PHP code base and content for new global corporate website

[WPML, Wordpress] \* System configuration and technical documentation [Homebrew, MySQL, WP-CLI, XML] \* Release management and issue tracking on source control [Markdown, GitLab]

### Sony DADC New Media Solutions

Dec 2013 to Jan 2016

**Software Engineer** 

@ rGenerator.com -- Digital branch of Sony DADC New Media Solutions

PLATFORM ENGINEER -- Continuous Integration [Git, GitHub, Capistrano, Jenkins Linux]

- \* Assuring high quality software by advancing and documenting Best Practices in SDLC for Enterprise web platform (WordPress)
- \* Release management; Automated testing, builds and deployment on stacked QA and Staging environment tiers
- \* High-availability production systems architecture [Varnish, EC2]

### **New York University**

Sep 2011 to Jan 2014

**Academic Technology Specialist** 

NYU ITS (Information Technology Services)

(ITSM): Google Apps for Ed (Email, Docs, Scripts).; NYU Stream [Kaltura Video Platform]; Web Publishing [WordPress]; and Wikis [Atlassian Confluence]; \* Wordpress theme development [PHP, MySQL], Google Script APIs [Javascript], Kaltura Mediaspace [PHP Zend Framework]

### **Tata Consultancy Services**

Jan 2008 to Dec 2008

**IT Consultant** 

Data Analyst @ Profuturo GNP - AFORE (financial group) \* Database Technical Writer [Oracle]: data models for modules of the business process. \* LAMP Developer [custom MVC PHP framework]: internal company website.

Business Analyst @ Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social (Social Security Institution) \* Technical Writer and Software Developer for the IMSS (Mexican Social Security Institute) [Java Enterprise, WebLogic, Struts & Hibernate, Maven]

#### **EDUCATION**

## **New York University**

2009 to 2013

Master in Music

Research Assitant at Music and Audio Research Laboratory http://marl.wikidot.com/

# Instituto Tecnológico y de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey

2000 to 2007

**Bachelor of Science (BS)** 

Including international program at University of Westminster, London, UK; Coursework in games and artificial intelligence.

Concurrently: grade 3 (diploma) in Music Theory by Royal Academy of Music (UK) 2005

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# Webpages Are Getting Larger Every Year, and Here's Why it Matters

Nov 15, 2018

https://royal.pingdom.com/

Webpage size matters because it correlates with how fast users get to your content. People today have

grown to expect good performance from the web. In fact, Google published data showing that 53% of mobile site visits are abandoned if a page takes longer than three seconds to load...

# Analyzing Heroku Router Logs with SolarWinds Loggly

Oct 23, 2018

loggly.com/blog

What are some common problems that can be detected with the handy router logs on Heroku? We'll explore them and show you how to address them easily with SolarWinds® Loggly® log management.

### **Analyzing Heroku Router Logs with Papertrail**

Sep 21, 2018

blog.papertrailapp.com

What are some common problems that can be detected with the handy router logs on Heroku? We'll explore them and show you how to address them easily and quickly with monitoring of Heroku from SolarWinds Papertrail.

# Benchmarking PHP Logging Frameworks: Which is Fastest and Most Reliable

Aug 23, 2018

loggly.com

The combination that provided the best performance and reliability is Log4j 2's ... for Loggly. Benchmarking Java Logging Frameworks ...

### **6 Key Linux Performance Metrics to Monitor**

May 29, 2018

blog.appoptics.com

Does your application run in a Linux environment? Make sure you have the best practices in monitoring Linux and know which metrics to monitor.

### **Monitor Django Web Applications**

May 2018

appoptics.com

Optimized for seamless integration and high performance, making it drop-dead simple to monitor your Django application metrics.

# Dockerize your Django App (for local development on macOS)

Mar 13, 2018

rehalcon.blogspot.com

Guide on how to containerize an existing (simple) Python Django App into Docker for local development

#### **HONORS**

## Google STEM Scholarship

Jan 2011

Google

Awarded a 1 year grant and a summer trip to scholars summit and conferenc in Mountainview, CA Processed by the Hispanic Scholarship Fund as a minority scholarship

## CONACYT Scholarship

Sep 2010

Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología

Prestigious 1 year grant and stipend for graduate studies abroad, granted by the Mexican National Science Council

<i>LANGUAGE</i> S	Spanish	
CERTIFICATIONS	ITIL Foundations CSME, Inc.	Jul 2013